Alan Guttmacher Institute records SSC.MS.00720
Sophia Smith Collection
- Guttmacher Institute research files, staff files and project records, 2018-S-0052; 7.5 linear feet (6 record cartons)
  - March of Dimes 1991, 10 folders (10 folders)
    The national project would have two main components: the collection of county level data on availability and accessibility of prenatal care and possibly of health care for children under age two. This information would be collected by MOD chapters, under the supervision of their national and regional staff, and with technical assistance from the AGI. MOD chapter staff and/or volunteers would survey providers using questionnaires and procedures designed by the AGI in consultation with the MOD. The AGI would be responsible for checking, editing, coding and keypunching survey questionnaires, for creating a clean computer file for analysis and for producing detailed tabulations. "-the compilation of new data on use of prenatal care services, similar to those published in the recent Institution publication: Prenatal Care in the United States: a State and County Inventory. This requires acquiring and processing detailed vital statistics files for 1987, 1988 and 1989. County level tabulations would be produced and analyzed."
    These project materials demonstrate the "behind the scenes" work that goes into a large-scale collaboration. They include information on the pilot study, correspondence, meeting notes and reports, proposals, and expense reports.
    - Pilot study handbook: March of Dimes Prenatal Care Needs Assessment, 1991 July; 1 items (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - March of Dimes prenatal care needs assessment questionnaire, 1991; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - March of Dimes/Guttmacher Institute pilot study, 1991-1992; 3 folders (3 folders) (Box 1)
    - March of Dimes memos, correspondence, publications and surveys, 1991; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - Correspondence between MoD and AGI, 1991; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - March of Dimes July meeting notes, 1991 July; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - March of Dimes proposal, 1991-1993; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - March of Dimes expenses, 1991; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
  - Identifying Service Changes to Improve Contraceptive Use, 3 folders (3 folders)
    "Goal: The goal of this project is to contribute to the improvement of contraceptive use and the reduction of unintended pregnancy in the United States. To achieve this goal, the project focuses on three interrelated objectives: 1) "To provide a comprehensive, national frame of reference or "map" of key factors contributing to poor contraceptive use from women's perspectives, by surveying a national sample of sexually active women at risk for unintended pregnancy. This information will enable us to assess the relative importance and priority of these factors based on their contribution to women's difficulties in using contraception effectively." 2) "To match this map with information on contraceptive delivery practices in order to identify changes that have the greatest potential to reduce unintended pregnancy, by collecting data from a national sample of publicly funded family planning clinics and private doctors." 3) "To identify policy and programmatic implications and make concrete recommendations for next steps in service delivery and research that will help move knowledge into practice so as to reduce unintended pregnancy in the United States."
    Includes project information, reports, and the following publications: "U.S. Women's One-Year Contraceptive Use Patterns, 2004" Perspectives on Sexual and Reproductive Health, 2007; "Factors Associated with Contraceptive Use and Nonuse, United States, 2004" Perspectives on Sexual and Reproductive Health, 2007; "Factors Associated with Contraceptive Choice and Inconsistent Method Use, United States, 2004" Perspectives on Sexual and Reproductive Health, 2008; "Public and Private Providers' Involvement in Improving Their Patients' Contraceptive Use" Elsevier 2008.
    - Key project information (findings, American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists correspondence), 2000-2006; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - Questionnaire development, physician's survey (planned publications by project, internal memos, survey cover letters, sample questionnaire), 1983-2005; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - Provider survey (extended follow-up of physicians by mail, telephone project final report, cover letter, IRB materials, questionnaires), 1982-2005; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
  - Cost of Contraceptive Coverage, 2 folders (2 folders)
    From the Project Description: "Contraceptive Coverage in the Age of Managed Care (19981999) With this one-year project, AGI will bring the best information to bear on the issue of access to contraceptive services and supplies through private insurance. The Institute will: 1) Assess issues and information from existing research that have the potential to enlist the support of diverse groups for the expansion of contraceptive coverage and explore remaining questions and possible areas of contention; 2) Synthesize and simplify existing research findings in a variety of public education materials; and raise awareness of the issues involved through dissemination, Web site posting and presentations to professional groups, organizations, opinion leaders and media selected for their ability to influence managed care organizations and consumers; 3) Monitor major state and federal policy developments which would ensure coverage of the full range of contraceptive options for women covered by private insurance." "Contraceptive Coverage in Private-sector Insurance Plans (1999) 1) To mobilize support for contraceptive insurance coverage within the private-sector, AGI will assemble and work with a task force composed of a diverse group of key employers and employee benefits managers; labor union negotiators; large employers, insurers and managed care plans. 2) In doing so, the Institute will identify arguments that may resonate with employers, insurers and managed care plans in order to persuade them to provide contraceptive coverage and messages that may convince labor unions and employee associations that contraceptive coverage is a vital component of employee health benefits and should be a priority in benefit-related contract negotiations with employers. 3) "Finally, AGI will develop and widely disseminate a comprehensive action plan for private sector-focused activitiesincluding funding needs for such a planand begin reaching out to key commercial audiences with research and policy analysis from AGI and others on women's contraceptive needs, the limitations of current coverage and the benefits of coverage that is comprehensive.
    "Contraceptive Coverage in Private-sector Insurance Plans (2001) 1) AGI has undertaken a series of activities to ensure that contraceptives are affordable to all Americans. First, the Institute convened a working grouprepresenting labor, business, women's and reproductive health organizationsto refine and adapt persuasive arguments (developed last year through AGI's contacts with business and insurance leaders) for the expansion of contraception in the private sector. The group is working to identify and involve new organizations and individuals that might be influential in the policy debate. This year, AGI will begin developing a methodology to quantify the costs and benefits of covering contraception in private insurance plans, to provide employers with a complete economic model they may consult in making coverage decisions. 2) AGI is also examining employer-based health plans to map trends, monitor the needs of the uninsured and document options for those without coverage. AGI is building on its accomplishments in advancing contraceptive coverage in the public sector by making staff expertise available to policymakers and activists who are working toward passage of the federal Equity in Prescription Insurance and Contraceptive Coverage Act and similar initiatives at the state level. 3) Last year, AGI began an update of its 1998 study to ascertain the coverage of reproductive health services, contraception and abortion within private insurance plans overall. This information helped spur state actions to mandate contraceptive coverage in private insurance plans (13 states to date). Upon publication, the findings will be used to inform new efforts aimed at meeting Americans' needs for services."
    Includes notes, internal memos, article drafts and handwritten notes.
    - Notes and internal memos, 2000-2002; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - Article drafts and handwritten notes, 2001-2003; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
  - PPFA Access to Services/Fee Survey/AGI Physician Survey, 6 folders (6 folders)
    These files relate to a 1986 project, PPFA Access to Services Teen Survey 1986.
    Many of these files contain surveys from the 1980s as well as internal memos. These folders were grouped together in the same storage box.
    - Fee Survey (questionnaires, cover letters, codebooks), 1983-1984; 1 folders (Box 1)
    - AGI physician survey (methodology and report), 1983; 1 folders (Box 1)
    - PP access, Summer 1985; 1 folders (Box 1)
    - PPFA access study, 1985; 1 folders (Box 1)
    - PPFA access study (coding and editing), 1985; 1 folders (Box 1)
    - Family Planning Services in Industrialized Countries, 1987-1989; 1 folders (Box 1)
  - Impact of the Restriction of Medicaid Funding for Abortion, 4 folders (4 folders)
    "Implementation of Congressional restrictions terminating federal funding for abortion except when necessary to save the life of the woman represents an extremely significant shift in U.S. public health policy. It has created an almost ideal laboratory for studying the consequences for both individuals and society of restricting access to abortion. The only previous case of such restriction occurred in Rumania in 1966. Michael S. Teitelbaum's study is now the classic reference concerning its impact on subsequent fertility, supplemented by Nicholas H. Wright's study of effects on maternal and child health. Since the restriction potentially affected every woman and no alternative means of fertility control were readily available, the analysis of Rumanian experience was comparatively simple. While the current U.S. situation is fraught with complexity, it nonetheless provides a rare opportunity to assess systematically the impact of such a policy change. The findings would be invaluable for both researchers and policymakers. It is therefore critical that evaluation efforts be planned and implemented without delay."
    Includes proposals, internal memos, correspondence, publications, figures, and meeting agendas.
    - Abortion - Medicaid - Lindheim Study, 1977-1979; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Medicaid - Lindheim - Survey: restriction of funding/abortion, 1977-1979; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Abortion funding publications, 1975-1979; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Ab XIX correspondence, memos, figures, 1977; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - STD Clinic Survey, 26 folders (26 folders)
    Final Article: Public Health Departments Providing Sexually Transmitted Disease Services Authors: David J. Landry and Jacqueline E. Darroch Published by the Guttmacher Institute in Family Planning Perspectives 1996 (now Perspectives on Sexual and Reproductive Health). Description of the Study: "This project will describe and assess the adequacy of the nation's publicly-funded sexually transmitted disease (STD) diagnostic treatment services. Information will be obtained by mailed survey from a nationally representative sample of publicly-funded agencies that provide STD services. The results from the survey will be compared with a 1995 AGI [Alan Guttmacher Institute] survey of agencies providing contraceptive services to identify gaps and overlaps between the STD and family planning service providers in outreach, clients served, services provided and referral arrangements. The project is funded under a grant from DHHS' Office of Population Affairs (OPA) through an interagency agreement with the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. It is a component of a wide-reaching Alan Guttmacher Institute project, funded by OPA, to reassess the nation's family planning and reproductive health needs."
    Includes meeting notes, development notes, correspondence, code, fieldwork, statistics, results, and general information about the project
    - IOM Report, 1995; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - STD SURV- pretest analysis, 1995; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - CDC meeting proofs, 1995 June 30; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - STD SURV meetings, 1995 Jan-Oct; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - STD SURV correspondence, 1995 May; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - STD SURV/CDC meeting in New York, 1996 March 25; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Questionnaire development and pretest analysis, 1995; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Pretest materials, 1995 May; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - NACCHO survey, 1995; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Sampling - NACCHO - CDC file, 1995; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Fieldwork- Arkansas, 1995 Dec; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - STD SURV- Est. of person days, 1995; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Non-response phone calls, 1995; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Clinic survey OPA (CDC), 1995; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Clinic survey 2nd mailing, 1995 Sept 28; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Clinic survey cover letter, 1st mailing, 1995; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Survey returns pretest, 1995; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - CDC - early sample, designs, etc, 1995; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Survey resends, clarifications, respondent comments, 1995; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Survey letters, 3rd mailing, 1995; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Field schedule information, 1995; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Non-response f-up/unit districts, 1995; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Coding rules, 1995; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Survey sampling, 1995; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Codebook questionnaires, 1995; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Unintended Pregnancy, 21 folders (21 folders)
    Purpose: "The purpose of the project is to examine how the fact of a pregnancy being unplanned affects the health of the baby at birth and during early infancy. It is assumed that any such influence operates through the effect of the planning status of the pregnancy on the mother's behavior, which is, in turn, a primary determinant of the baby's well-being. The underlying hypothesis is that the unintended conception is associated with less personal input to promote the baby's health both during pregnancy and after the baby is bornThe investigation will evaluate the impact of unplanned pregnancy on women's behavior in two principal areas. The first consists of activities during pregnancy, and the second is care of the infant after birth. It is not possible, however, to identify and test the effects of planning status on all behaviors that could have a bearing on the health of the child. For this reason and because the ultimate significance of the mother's behavior lies in its close association with the health of her infant, the indirect relationships between planning status and measure of the baby's well-being will also be examined."
    Publications: 1) "Intention Status of U.S. Births in 1988: Differences by Mothers' Socioeconomic and Demographic Characteristics" Family Planning Perspectives, 1995. Kathryn Kost and Jacqueline Darroch Forrest. 2) "The Effects of Pregnancy Planning Status on Birth Outcomes and Infant Care" Family Planning Perspectives, 1998. Kathryn Kost, David J. Landry, and Jacqueline E. Darroch. 3) "Predicting Maternal Behaviors During Pregnancy: Does Intention Status Matter?" Family Planning Perspectives, 1998. Kathryn Kost, David J. Landry, and Jacqueline E. Darroch.
    Includes planning meeting information and notes, financial and grant information, papers and drafts, and data.
    - Galleys Stage I, Products, 1998; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Intention Status (try 1), 1992-1994; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Institute of Medicine (IOM), 1993-1994; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Meetings/advisory panel, 1995-1998; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - National Institute of Child Health and Human Development planning proposal, 1992-1994; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - National Institute of Child Health and Human Development planning status - financials, 1993-1996; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Shannon Grant, 1992-1994; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Preg. behavior article (Family Planning Perspectives), 1997-1998; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Year II financials, 1995; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Year III financials, 1996; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Unintended pregnancy - 2nd article, 1997-1998; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Advisory meeting materials, 1994 Nov-Dec; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Planning status proposal, 1991; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Population Association of America (PAA) paper and drafts, 1997; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Planning status - consult with Rodriguez, 1995 Oct 15; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Stage I final stepwise, 1995 Aug 1-Aug 8; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - January 1997 meetings, 1997 Jan; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Data documentation, 1997 Jan; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Stage II Vars: birth characteristics, 1994-1995; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Action articles (drafts), 1997; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Proposals and articles, 1993-1998; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - "TP3" project files, or, "Successes of the Past, Opportunities for the Future: Reevaluating Teenage Pregnancy in the 1990s", 19 folders (15 folders, contents of two binders in four folders)
    From the Funding Proposal to the Charles Stewart Mott Foundation: "Summary: The Alan Guttmacher Institute (AGI) proposes to refocus and reorient attention on the problems of teenage sexual activity, pregnancy, abortion, and childbearing for the 1990s. To do so, AGI will collect and analyze the most recent information on these issues, synthesize the data, and present the findings, conclusions and recommendations in a new chartbook. Like its immediate predecessor, the Institute's 1981 Teenage Pregnancy: The Problem That Hasn't Gone Away, the updated version is intended to be a major source of information, presenting complicated research data in a simple and cohesive fashion and pointing to opportunities for policy and program action. With this publication, AGI will place teenage pregnancy within the larger context of what has been learned about adolescent and high-risk behavior in recent years as well as in the context of the concurrent increase in poverty, the decrease in services, the attacks on family planning programs, the growth of AIDS among adolescents, and the need for reproductive health services among young people. To enhance the chartbook's effectiveness, an extensive public education/outreach effort will be targeted to an audience of 5,000 policymakers, program planners, community leaders, activists, professionals working with youth and the press."
    Information from all stages of the project, including proposals, drafts, meeting notes, figures and comments, questionnaires, and general notes.
    - Teen Pregnancy 3 meeting notes, 1992; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 3)
    - MCHB meeting, 1993 Oct 6; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 3)
    - Gag rule information, 1991; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 3)
    - Advisory panel meeting, 1992 Sept 18; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 3)
    - TP3 Edit #2 figures only, comments from OSN, 1993 Dec 30; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 3)
    - TP3 Meeting round 4, 1993 Oct 20; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 3)
    - David Landry (DL) notes for TP3 draft #3, 1993 Oct 18; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 3)
    - TP3 Draft #2, 1993 Sept 21; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 3)
    - TP3 Draft #3 meeting, 1993 Oct 20; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 3)
    - Questionnaires, 1992; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 3)
    - Other Guttmacher related publications, 1993; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 3)
    - TP3 projects in progress, 1992; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 3)
    - NMIHS (National Maternal and Infant Health Survey) notes, 1993; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 3)
    - Background for TP3, 1990-1992; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 3)
    - TP3 final paper articles and references, 1987-1994; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 3)
    - Binder of figures and proposal, 1992-1994; 2 folders (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Binder of project notes and figures, 1992-1994; 2 folders (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Christopher Tietze files, 18 folders (18 folders)
    Christopher Tietze, a physician and respected authority on abortion, contraception, and pregnancy, began working for the Population Council in the 1970s. He authored several iterations of the report "Induced Abortion: A World Review." At the time of his death in 1984, Tietze was in the process of compiling the sixth edition of this fact book. The Guttmacher Institute undertook the completion of this project.
    These files mostly consist of Tietze's correspondence and handwritten statistics sent to him by health officials around the world. What is particularly compelling about these files is that they represent the work that Tietze did in his final years, and the folder in Box 2 "1985 Abortion Fact Book" contains copies of the letters that he dictated on his last ever day in the office.
    - "1975 and before = gestation and gest x age" (statistics), approx 1975; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 4)
    - Abortion Fact Book clippings, notes, statistics, correspondence, 1968-1985; 13 folders (13 folders) (Box 4)
    - "Deaging Data", 1973-1980; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 4)
    - "Induced Abortion: A World Review" by Christopher Tietze, 1983; 1 items (1 book) (Box 4)
    - World Health Organization mortality from abortion stats, 1983; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 4)
    - Tietze correspondence, 1984; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 4)
  - Abortion in Guatemala, 9 folders (9 folders)
    These files relate to research that took place in the mid-2000s about abortion in Central America. While these files primarily relate to abortion in Guatemala, there are some folders that contain information about Honduras and Nicaragua.
    Although these files give a less complete picture of the project, there are outlines and subsequent drafts that demonstrate the process of preparing a paper for publication. Files in this box are in both English and Spanish.
    - Drafts, notes, articles, and email correspondence, 2005-2006; 2 folders (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Outlines, drafts, and reviews, 2006-2007; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 5)
    - "ACA: references to look up" email correspondence and memos, 2004-2005; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 5)
    - "RIB-2s General (all 3 countries)" (paper reviews and correspondence), 2006-2007; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 5)
    - HPS/HFS post-abortion care forms, 2003; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 5)
    - "Honduras RIB-2" (information about Honduras in English and Spanish), 2001-2007; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 5)
    - "Nicaragua RIB-2" (information about Nicaragua, English and Spanish), 2005-2006; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 5)
    - Guttmacher publications, 1993-2006; 2 folders (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - 5 Year Plan files, 58 folders (58 folders)
    These [files] are the entire contents of a box sent to storage in 1998. These files were deemed to be significant, and Guttmacher decided that they would be best preserved and utilized at the Sophia Smith Collection.